<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V4.1.2//EN" "docbook/xml-dtd-4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <date>2003-06-06</date>
    <title>mspgcc and C for the MSP430 FAQ</title>
    <subtitle>FAQ</subtitle>
    <releaseinfo>documentation in progress</releaseinfo>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Steve</firstname>
        <surname>Underwood</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <address>
      <email>steveu@coppice.org</email>
    </address>
    <copyright>
      <year>2003</year>
      <holder>Steve Underwood</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      <para>
        This document can be freely redistributed according to the
        terms of the GNU General Public License.
      </para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

<para>This FAQ discusses a range of common issues related to programming the MSP430. More
specifically, to programming the MSP430 in C. Most specifically to programming the MSP430
using the mspgcc toolchain.</para>

<sect1 id="q1">
<title>Using C to program a small MCU produces slow bulky programs, doesn't it?</title>
<para>You've been programming 8051s for too long. :-)</para>
<para>Seriously, an MCU like the MSP430 programs well in C. You can always beat the
efficiency of any compiler if you try really hard in assembly language. However, you do
have to make a real effort to get substantially better performance on good modern MCUs, not
just the MSP430, when using a good C compiler.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="q2">
<title>I still have resort to some assembly language for things like interrupt routines,
and controlling the lower power modes, right?</title>
<para>Wrong! mspgcc has simple extensions to the standard C language are provided to make
interrupt service routines easy to write, without a single line of assembly language. Facilities
are provided for controlling the MSP430's lower power modes, too. See the mspgcc manual for
details.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="q3">
<title>I will still need to use some assembly language somewhere, won't I?</title>
<para>This is no more or less true for an MSP430 C program, than for a C program anywhere
else. For example, a "Where is the first 1 in this word?" instruction exists on many
large modern processors (x86, Alpha, etc.). You don't have to use it, but it can really
speed up certain types of code. You can only make use of it with assembly language
programming. However, that can be as simple as a single line of embedded assembly
language in the middle of a C routine. This is no different with the MSP430.</para>

<para>As an example, an area where you might choose to use assembly language in
this way is to access the BCD facilities of the MSP430. Many people like to use
BCD for a variety of things, in small embedded projects. Like most other
processors, the MSP430 has decimal adjust instructions to make this
straightforward. You can only gain access to those through assembly language.
However, the assembly language need only be a few simple routines you create
once and reuse. They can be simple functions, like:
<programlisting role="C">
void bin2bcd16(register uint8_t bcd[3], register uint16_t bin)
{
    register int i;
    register uint16_t decimal_0;
    register uint16_t decimal_1;

    i = 16;
    decimal_0 =
    decimal_1 = 0;
    __asm__ __volatile__(
        "1: \n"
        " rla   %[bin] \n"
        " dadd  %[decimal_0],%[decimal_0] \n"
        " dadd  %[decimal_1],%[decimal_1] \n"
        " dec   %[i] \n"
        " jnz   1b \n"
        " mov.b %[decimal_1],0(%[bcd]) \n"
        " mov.b %[decimal_0],2(%[bcd]) \n"
        " swpb  %[decimal_0] \n"
        " mov.b %[decimal_0],1(%[bcd]) \n"
        : [bcd] "+r"(bcd), [decimal_0] "+r"(decimal_0), [decimal_1] "+r"(decimal_1)
        : [bin] "r"(bin), [i] "r"(i));
}
</programlisting>
which will convert a 16 bit binary value to a BCD string stored in a byte array.
They could be simple inlined routines, for very arithmetic operations. Being
inlined means there will be no call overhead, so it is clean, compact, and fast.
For example:
<programlisting role="C">
static __inline__ uint16_t bcd_add16(register uint16_t bcd_a, register uint16_t bcd_b)
{
    __asm__(
	" clrc \n"
        " dadd %[bcd_b],%[bcd_a] \n"
        : [bcd_a] "+ro" (bcd_a)
        : [bcd_b] "g" (bcd_b));
    return bcd_a;
}
</programlisting>
will add two 4 digit BCD values, stored as unsigned integers, and return the
4 digit BCD result, as an unsigned integer. Create a few routines like this,
and you need not touch any assembly language for the rest of your project.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="q4">
<title>This thing is free, so it's second rate. Right?</title>
<para>The GNU tools are used extensively in commercial work. It is naive to equate cost
with value. The mspgcc port is currently stable, and being used to produce good quality
commercial code. Other tools provide a more integrated GUI appearance, but do not offer
much extra that is of real substance.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="q5">
<title>Where's the IDE? Development tools are worthless without an IDE.</title>
<para>Whatever gave you that strange idea? Most IDEs offer a poor project manager, a poor
editor and a poor debugger - poor tools, but really well integrated!</para>

<para>Excellent freely available editors, like
<ulink url="http://www.scintilla.org/SciTE.html">SciTE</ulink>, allow you to edit,
compile, jump straight to the lines with syntax errors, and so on. GUI debugger
front ends, such as
<ulink url="http://sources.redhat.com/insight">Insight</ulink>,
<ulink url="http://libre.act-europe.fr/gvd/main.html">GVD</ulink>,
<ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/ddd">DDD</ulink>, etc., provide source
level debug features as good or better than most other offerings.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="q6">
<title>Without a IDE project manager it is a pain to compile code. What do I do?</title>
<para>Learn about make. Most IDEs just provide a front end to a program called make.
Versions of make exist on most platforms. The Windows installer for mspgcc includes a
copy of the GNU version of make. On most other platforms, you probably already have a
make program installed.</para>

<para>It takes little time to get used to the basics of make, and the make files for
most projects are just a few lines long. It is a simple scripting tool, to define how
your software is to be built. When you edit your source code, and run make it will rebuilt
only what is necessary, on the basis of the files which have changed. The GNU documentation
can be found at <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/make/make.html">the GNU make home
page</ulink>.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="q7">
<title>But I know from the past that the GNU GCC compiler is not the world's most efficient.
Right?</title>
<para>If you have used older versions of GCC you may well have formed that opinion. GCC has
always been good for development, but older versions where not so efficient for runtime use.
That changed a lot with the release of version, 3.0. Version 3.2.3 (the current basis for
mspgcc) produces code that is very competitive in both size and speed. The mspgcc uses
the facilities optimisation provided by GCC well, and produces very competitive code.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="q8">
<title>The mspgcc manual doesn't really describe the GNU tools. Why?</title>
<para>Extensive documentation, in multiple formats and languages, exists for the GNU tools.
mspgcc is a port of those tools, and has all their standard features, plus a few special
ones. Documenting all the standard things would be a waste of time, and probably confusing
to those familiar with the GNU tools for other targets. The mspgcc documentation only seeks to
document things which are special to mspgcc.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="q9">
<title>I've used the IAR compiler to program an MSP430, and it has a few nice features to
access the special features of the MSP430. What does mspgcc have?</title>
<para>In general, mspgcc has similar facilities to the IAR tools. The syntax is a little
different in some cases. For example, declaring a routine as an interrupt service routine
requires round brackets, instead of square ones, around the vector name. However, just a
little editing, and a few "#if defined(__GNUC__)"s will allow a program to compile with
either the IAR or the mspgcc tools. In fact, just a little more work should allow programs
to compile with the Quadravox or Rowley compilers, too.</para>

<para>The way embedded assembly language is handled is the biggest difference between source
code for these compilers. This is likely to be the greatest source of code porting work, assuming
you have resorted to using assembly language.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="q10">
<title>IAR provide a function to get a frame address of a function, allowing you more control.
Does mspgcc have anything similar?</title>
<para>GCC provides the function "__builtin_frame_address(LEVEL)", but this will not help you
much, unless R4 is being used as a frame pointer. With optimisation switched on, it will not.
Of course, mspgcc has a real solution to this problem. Look in the Calls Definition section
of the mspgcc manual for information on ".L__FrameSize". Of course, mspgcc also has things like
"_BIC_SR_IRQ()" and "_BIS_SR_IRQ()", which simplify the most common reasons to work directly with
the frame address.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="q11">
<title>When I link my files with msp430-ld it keeps saying
"undefined reference to `__stop_progExec__'". What's up?</title>
<para>You forgot to link a couple of things - startup code, interrupt vectors and libraries.
The proper linker command looks something like:
<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>msp430-ld -m msp430x[arch]
/usr/local/msp430/bin/../lib/gcc-lib/msp430/3.2.3/../../../../msp430/lib/crt430x[arch].o
-L/usr/local/msp430/bin/../lib/gcc-lib/msp430/3.2.3/msp1
-L/usr/local/msp430/bin/../lib/gcc-lib/msp430/3.2.3
-L/usr/local/msp430/bin/../lib/gcc-lib
-L/usr/local/msp430//lib/gcc-lib/msp430/3.2.3/msp1
-L/usr/local/msp430//lib/gcc-lib/msp430/3.2.3
-L/usr/local/msp430/bin/../lib/gcc-lib/msp430/3.2.3/../../../../msp430/lib/msp1
-L/usr/local/msp430/bin/../lib/gcc-lib/msp430/3.2.3/../../../../msp430/lib
-L/usr/local/msp430//lib/gcc-lib/msp430/3.2.3/../../../../msp430/lib/msp1
-L/usr/local/msp430//lib/gcc-lib/msp430/3.2.3/../../../../msp430/lib
-L/usr/local/msp430/bin/../lib/gcc-lib/msp430/3.2.3/../../..
[object file].o -lgcc -lc -lgcc</userinput>
</screen>
Of course, this is a pain to type, so don't! The simple way is to use msp430-gcc as
a front end to the linker. Then you can just type:
<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>msp430-gcc -mmcu=[arch] -L[extra libraries path] -l[extra libs] obj1.o obj2.o ... -o outputfile</userinput>
</screen>
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="q12">
<title>I need to place a chunk of data in its own page in flash memory, so I can erase and
reprogram that page without erasing anything else. How can I do that?</title>
<para>This is a typical requirement for an application with large calibration tables.
There are two ways to deal with this. You can use a custom linker script, or special
command line arguments to the linker. In either case you will want to tag the items to
be placed in your special area, so the linker can identify them. the following illustrates
how to do this:
<programlisting role="C">
#define __special_area__ __attribute__((section(".specialarea")))

void __special_area__ special_routine(int x, float y);

const __special_area__ int my_const = MY_VALUE;
</programlisting>
The attribute "__special_area__" may be used with any other attributes in defining routines and
data. At link time, the linker will associate all these with the section ".specialarea".
Either your custom linker file, or command line parameters must define this section.</para>

<para>The easiest way to make a custom linker script is to start from the standard one
for the device you are using. You can adjust the boundaries of the existing sections, and
add new ones to lay out your code and data any way you want in memory. The linker
script language is defined in the documentation for binutils. A compiler command such as:
<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>msp430-gcc -Wl,--section-start -Wl,-T linker_script.x [other necessary options and files]</userinput>
</screen>
Specifies that the customer linker script "linker_script.x" should be used in place of the
default one.</para>
<para>For the simple definition of one special section, it may be easier to just define that
section on the command line with a command such as:
<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>msp430-gcc -Wl,--section-start -Wl,.newsection=0xd400 [other necessary options and files]</userinput>
</screen>
which will place .newsection at address 0xd4000. Although this will place objects where you
want them, it may not reliably fulfill your requirement. it will not ensure that nothing else
goes in the relevant page of the flash memory, which would cause trouble if you need to erase
that page. Defining your data to be the exact size of one or more flash memory pages, and
forcing that data to start at the required page boundary will be reliable. The following
example uses a union to ensure the overall size of your data block is well known:
<programlisting role="C">
#define __special_area__ __attribute__((section(".specialarea")))

const __special_area__ union
{
    char force[512];
    struct
    {
        int a;
        int b;
        char c[10];
        float d;
    };
} my_erasable_data_area;
</programlisting>
Bear in mind that startup code (if linked) will start from the ROM's first address. Its
size is 0x40 (including _reset_vector__(), _unexpected_() and _unexpected_1_(), providing
last two are not redefined in your code).</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="q13">
<title>I want to jump from some arbitrary places to my exception handling code, to
deal with fatal error conditions. Is it possible to do this with mspgcc?</title>
<para>Any standards compliant implementation of C, including mspgcc, supports this feature, with
the routines setjmp() and longjmp(). The following example illustrates their use, with two
destinations to jump to. You may define any number of destinations. You may jumps from
anywhere, even from an interrupt service routine, and the stack will be properly cleaned up:
<programlisting role="C">
#include &lt;setjmp.h&gt;

jmp_buf __jmp_a;    /* make this global */
jmp_buf __jmp_b;    /* make this global */

void first_place_to_jump_from(void)
{
    ...
    if (something1)
        longjmp(__jmp_a, 1);
    if (something2)
        longjmp(__jmp_b, 123);
    ...
}

type second_place_to_jump_from(...)
{
    ...
    if (something3)
        longjmp(__jmp_a, 2);
    ...
}

void the_place_to_jump_to(void)
{
    int res;
    ...

    res = setjmp(__jmp_a);
    switch (res)
    {
    case 0:
        /* Not a jump. Just normal program flow. */
        res = setjmp(__jmp_b);
        switch (res)
        {
        case 0:
            /* Not a jump. Just normal program flow. */
            break;
        case 123:
            /* We jumped here from the first subroutine */
            break;
        }
        break;
    case 1:
        /* We jumped here from the first subroutine */
        break;
    case 2:
        /* We jumped here from second routine */
        break;
    }
    for (;;)
    {
        first_place_to_jump_from();
        second_place_to_jump_from();
    }
}
</programlisting>
</para>
</sect1>
</article>
</book>
